{
  "reference_number": "11387",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Clear target must be set in legislation now. We need a more ambitious target: net zero emissions by 2040. Becuase its necessary to\n act swiftly to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and avoid a global tipping point"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "It is important to address all types of greenhouse gases, including nitrous oxide, methane, HFCs and other fluorinated gases. Even\n short-lived GHGs can have signficiant effect on climate, and could trigger a tipping point. The target must cover all sources of\n\n emissions, including agriculture, transport, industrial activities, refrigeration/air conditioning sectors, waste, and actions that will help\n individual citizens to reduce their own GHG footprint. Activities should include significant GHG reduction actions that are not often\n\n addressed, such as: (a) Government policies/actions that help consumers to consume fewer goods, and avoid throw-away products\n (eg. establishing durability standards and obligatory recycling requirements for household appliances; banning single-use plastic\n bags; promoting standardised re-usable containers for drinks and food products, etc.) (b) Government policies/actions that help\n\n citizens to have fewer children, i.e. strong government support for family planning and birth control. Each person born in an\n industrialised country has a far larger carbon footprint than each person living in a developing country. Reducing the number of births\n in industrialised countries will have a significant impact on global emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Its important to meet national targets by reducing domestic emissions only. New forest planting should focus on native tree species\n\n primarily"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No, the target date cannot be put back. However, yes, it is acceptable to strengthen the target, ie. bring forward the target date for\n zero net emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes and no, based on the following conditions: I oppose Government having the ability to make changes that would make the\n emissions budget weaker or slower at addressing climate change. I support Government having the ability to make the emissions\n budget more stringent (ie. faster action to address climate change) (Your standard answers do not give enough options)"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes and no, based on the following conditions: I oppose Government having the ability to make changes that would make the\nemissions budget weaker or slower at addressing climate change. I support Government having the ability to make the emissions\n\nbudget more stringent (ie. faster action to address climate change)"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However, Highest priority should be given to environmental protection. Environmental protection must be given clear priority over the\ncompetitiveness of specific sectors of the economy. New Zealand needs to move away from dinosaur economic sectors, and focus\non supporting sectors that will be genuinely environmentally sustainable"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Within 6 months. A strict time frame needs to be specified."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Environmental protection should have the highest priority. New Zealand needs to move away from dinosaur economic sectors, and\nfocus on supporting sectors that will be genuinely environmentally sustainable"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However, the Government should be legally required to consider and formally respond to the Commission’s advice, and provide an\n\nexplanation if they do not plan to act on it. In such cases, the Climate Change Commission should also have an obligation to provide a\npublic report that responds to, and critiques, the Government’s explanation. The CC Commissions’ report should specify a set of\n\nclear action steps that would enable the Government to meet the targets and advice"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission should have a role in advising policy for changing the NZ ETS, so that the NZ ETS scheme will\nsubstantially reduce emissions ETS schemes are not effective if they mainly move emissions from one location to another. The NZ\n\nETS has been a very weak instrument to date. If the NZ ETS scheme continues, it must have clear goals for substantially reducing\nGHG emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Commission needs to be an independent expert body, with the clear aim of providing detailed information on how to reduce\ngreenhouse gas emissions to net zero Members should be experts/specialists in climate change policy who also have proven\n\nknowledge of effective activities that will reduce greenhouse gas emissions to meet the net zero goal Members must never\nrepresent the interests of stakeholder groups or specific sectors It is only acceptable to include ETS experts if they have in-depth\nknowledge of ETS schemes that substantially reduce GHG emissions. ETS schemes are not acceptable if they mainly move\n\nemissions from one location to another."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, provided that this does not detract from the emissions reduction work of the Commission. It may be necessary to have a\n\nseparate but linked group that reports on adaptation measures"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Companies and organisations should be required to publish such information, eg. insurance companies, local councils, estate agents\n\nLocal councils should identify all land areas and buildings that will be subject to climate-related risks, and make that information\npublicly available online and in LIM reports Estate agent property sales information should include local council’s climate change risks\nfor each property Much more focus should be placed on prohibiting building and development on land that is likely to experience\n\nstorm surges, flooding or significant damage arising from climate change"
    }
  ]
}
